<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>log.j38.uk</title>
    <link>https://log.j38.uk</link>
    <description>A minimalist blog</description>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 17:17:09 GMT</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://log.j38.uk/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <item>
      <title>2026-02-10_1770732189</title>
      <link>https://log.j38.uk/2026-02-10_1770732189.html</link>
      <guid>https://log.j38.uk/2026-02-10_1770732189.html</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>οὕτως ἀταλαίπωρος τοῖς πολλοῖς ἡ ζήτησις τῆς ἀληθείας, καὶ ἐπὶ τὰ ἑτοῖμα μᾶλλον τρέπονται.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>So averse to taking pains are most men in the search for the truth, and so prone are they to turn to what lies ready at hand (tr. C.F. Smith).</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Thucydides 1.20.3</p>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2026-02-10_1770730219</title>
      <link>https://log.j38.uk/2026-02-10_1770730219.html</link>
      <guid>https://log.j38.uk/2026-02-10_1770730219.html</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>There is not really any courage at all in attacking hoary or antiquated
things, any more than in offering to fight one&#39;s grandmother. The really
courageous man is he who defies the tyrannies young as the morning and
superstitions fresh as the first flowers. The only true free thinker is he
whose intellect is as much free from the future as from the past.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>G.K. Chesterton</p>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2026-02-10_1770728850</title>
      <link>https://log.j38.uk/2026-02-10_1770728850.html</link>
      <guid>https://log.j38.uk/2026-02-10_1770728850.html</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>“You must not imagine,” says Nicole, “that the life of study is an easy life…
The reason is that there is nothing more against nature than uniformity and
stillness, because nothing gives us more occasion to be alone with ourselves.
Change and external occupations take us out of ourselves and distract us by
making us forget ourselves. Moreover, this medium of words has always
something dead about it, it has nothing that piques our self-love or rouses
our passions strongly. It is devoid of action and movement… It speaks little
to us of ourselves and gives us little ground for contemplating ourselves
with pleasure. It affords little encouragement to our hopes; and all this
tends strangely to mortify our self-love, which, be­ing unsatisfied, causes
us weariness and distaste in everything that we do.” This analysis, which
re­calls Pascal’s theory of diversion^1 might take us far. I merely pick out
the fact that as “weariness and distaste” are in our case formidable enemies,
we must plan to overcome them.  </p>
<p>1: Divertissement: literally, the word means turning aside from ourselves and
our destiny to find distraction in occupations, amusements, etc. “The whole
calamity of man” (wrote Pascal) “comes from one single thing, that he cannot
keep quiet in a room.” That is the cause of all our misfortunes; and if we
look for the reason of this restlessness we shall find that there is an
effectual one, the craving to evade the vision of our destiny.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Sertillanges, The Intellectual Life, 215ff. (quoting Nicole, a 17th century French moralist)</p>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2026-02-09_1770698752</title>
      <link>https://log.j38.uk/2026-02-09_1770698752.html</link>
      <guid>https://log.j38.uk/2026-02-09_1770698752.html</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>ἀμήχανον δὲ παντὸς ἀνδρὸς ἐκμαθεῖν ψυχήν τε καὶ φρόνημα καὶ γνώμην, πρὶν ἂν ἀρχαῖς τε καὶ νόμοισιν ἐντριβὴς φανῇ.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It is impossible to discover the temper, mind and will of a man, until he is proved by exercise of power.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Creon in Sophocles, Antigone 175-7.</p>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2026-02-09_1770698331</title>
      <link>https://log.j38.uk/2026-02-09_1770698331.html</link>
      <guid>https://log.j38.uk/2026-02-09_1770698331.html</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>… you must defend your solitude with a fierceness that makes no distinctions
whatever. If you have duties, satisfy their demands at the normal time; if you
have friends, arrange suitable meetings; if unwanted visitors come to disturb
you, graciously shut the door on them.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It is important, during the hours sacred to work, not only that you should
not be disturbed, but that you should know you will not be disturbed; let
perfect security on that score protect you, so that you can apply yourself
intensely and fruitfully. You cannot take too many precautions about this.
Keep a Cerberus at your door. Every demand on you from outside is a loss of
inner power and may cost your mind some precious discovery: “when the
half-gods go, the gods arrive.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Sertillanges, <em>The Intellectual Life</em> 98</p>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2026-01-29</title>
      <link>https://log.j38.uk/2026-01-29.html</link>
      <guid>https://log.j38.uk/2026-01-29.html</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>Philosophy is the science of Life. Its problem is to find the Ultimate from
which we may explain the origin of man and nature, determine the laws of
their growth, obtain a presentiment of their destiny, and become inspired
with a pure and noble zeal to live and die for the glory of God, and the
progress of mankind.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There is and can be no higher problem than this, none more worthy to engage
the whole force of our minds and our hearts. It is the problem of problems;
it includes all other problems; and on its solution depend all other problems
for theirs. We have answered no question, whether of man or nature, of
society, religion, or morals, till we have traced it to the Ultimate, beyond
which there is no question to be asked, or to be answered.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>But the Ultimate for ever escapes us. It recedes always in proportion as we
advance; and is never seized save in a finite and relative form. The complete
solution, therefore, transcends, and for ever must transcend, the reach of
our powers. All that we can do, and all that we should attempt, is to obtain
the solution that shall meet the wants and satisfy the heart of our own
epoch. This solution, though it must one day needs be outgrown, as we outgrow
the garments of our childhood, will, nevertheless, bring us a measure of
peace, become the point of departure for new inquirers, and pave the way for
new and more adequate solutions.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Orestes Brownson. &quot;Synthetic Philosophy&quot;</p>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2026-01-22</title>
      <link>https://log.j38.uk/2026-01-22.html</link>
      <guid>https://log.j38.uk/2026-01-22.html</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>It is easy to lie with statistics, but easier to lie without them.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Frederick Mosteller</p>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2025-11-06</title>
      <link>https://log.j38.uk/2025-11-06.html</link>
      <guid>https://log.j38.uk/2025-11-06.html</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>&quot;Is there, in all republics, this inherent, and fatal weakness?  Must a government, of necessity, be too strong for the liberties of its own people, or too weak to maintain its own existence?&quot;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Abraham Lincoln (July 4 1861)</p>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2025-10-19</title>
      <link>https://log.j38.uk/2025-10-19.html</link>
      <guid>https://log.j38.uk/2025-10-19.html</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>The philosopher today is therefore pressed, and simply by reason of his objective social role in the community, into an imitation of the scientist: he too seeks to perfect the weapons of his knowledge through specialization. Hence the extraordinary preoccupation with technique among modern philosophers, with logical and linguistic analysis, syntax and semantics; and in general with the refining away of all content for the sake of formal subtlety. The movement known as Logical Positivism, in this country (the atmosphere of humanism is probably more dominant in the European universities than here in the United States), actually trafficked upon the <em>guilt</em> philosophers felt at not being scientists; that is, at not being researchers producing reliable knowledge in the mode of science. The natural insecurity of philosophers, which in any case lies at the core of their whole uncertain enterprise, was here aggravated beyond measure by the insistence that they transform themselves into scientists.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Barret, <em>Irrational Man</em> 6</p>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2025-09-29</title>
      <link>https://log.j38.uk/2025-09-29.html</link>
      <guid>https://log.j38.uk/2025-09-29.html</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>The understanding, like the eye, whilst it makes us see and perceive all other things, takes no notice of itself; and it requires art and pains to set it at a distance, and make it its own object.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Locke</p>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2025-09-17</title>
      <link>https://log.j38.uk/2025-09-17.html</link>
      <guid>https://log.j38.uk/2025-09-17.html</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>I am active in as true and high a sense in my unconscious operations, as in what are properly called my volitions.  If this were not so, moral character could attach only to those acts which are performed after deliberation, which is not true. The real moral character of the man is determined, almost solely, by his spontaneous operations, the unconscious motions of his soul.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Brownson</p>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>1980_wendell-berry</title>
      <link>https://log.j38.uk/1980_wendell-berry.html</link>
      <guid>https://log.j38.uk/1980_wendell-berry.html</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>Increasingly over the last maybe forty years, the thought has come to me that
the old world in which our people lived by the work of their hands, close to
weather and earth, plants and animals was the true world; and that the new
world of cheap energy and ever cheaper money, honored greed, and dreams of
liberation from every restraint, is mostly theater. This new world seems a
jumble of scenery and props never quite believable, an economy of fantasies
and moods, in which it is hard to remember either the timely world of nature
or the eternal world of the prophets and poets.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Wendell Berry.  <em>Andy Catlett: Early Travels</em>.  Shoemaker &amp; Hoard, 2006. p. 93</p>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>1980_wendell_berry_153730</title>
      <link>https://log.j38.uk/1980_wendell_berry_153730.html</link>
      <guid>https://log.j38.uk/1980_wendell_berry_153730.html</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>The threat to domestic tranquility is not that people take sides and disagree, but that the sides of a political division will assume the purity and passion of moral absolutism or moral allegory, in which the people on each side think of themselves as Good and of the people on the other side as Evil. The passions on both sides then are reduced to mere anger, fear, and hatred. A society with an absurdly attenuated sense of sin starts talking then of civil war or holy war, and trending toward the psychology of the battlefield. So absolute a division forbids actual thought or discourse about moral issues, as it forbids self-knowledge, humor, and forgiveness. It may be that such division is prepared by our convention of two political parties.  It may be that actual thought about a problem requires more than two opinions. </p>
</blockquote>
<p>Wendell Berry, <em>The Need to be Whole</em>, 188-9.</p>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>1980_wendell_berry</title>
      <link>https://log.j38.uk/1980_wendell_berry.html</link>
      <guid>https://log.j38.uk/1980_wendell_berry.html</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>Obviously, we <em>can</em> work on a gigantic scale, but just as obviously we cannot foresee the gigantic catastrophes to which gigantic works are vulnerable, any more than we can foresee the natural and human consequences of such work.  We can develop a global economy, but only on the conditions that it will not be loving in its effects on its human and natural sources, and that it will risk global economic collapse.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Wendell Berry, “Two Minds” in <em>Citizenship Papers</em>, 104-5.</p>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>1980_vonneumann</title>
      <link>https://log.j38.uk/1980_vonneumann.html</link>
      <guid>https://log.j38.uk/1980_vonneumann.html</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>If people do not believe that mathematics is simple, it is only because they do not realize how complicated life is.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>John von Neumann</p>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>1980_szlezak</title>
      <link>https://log.j38.uk/1980_szlezak.html</link>
      <guid>https://log.j38.uk/1980_szlezak.html</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>Plato tells us with all clarity that his philosophy demands the whole human being. Intellectual capability alone is insufficient; what is required is an inner relationship between the thing which is to be conveyed and the soul to which it is to be conveyed. Anybody who is not prepared to enter upon a process of inner transformation is not entitled to know the full solution either.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Thomas A. Szlezák, <em>Reading Plato</em>.</p>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>1980_st-edith-stein</title>
      <link>https://log.j38.uk/1980_st-edith-stein.html</link>
      <guid>https://log.j38.uk/1980_st-edith-stein.html</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>  What has been called St. Thomas&#39;s &quot;system&quot; took shape in this work of assembling, sifting, ordering.
The body of knowledge of his time became ordered in his mind.  He wrote no &quot;philosophical system,&quot;
nor has the system behind his works been written so far.  </p>
<p>  Yet anyone who studies his works will find clear, definite answers, perhaps to more questions than he
himself could ask.  And what is more, the <em>organon</em> that the Master bore within himself and that enabled
him to settle a host of issues with a firm, serene <em>respondeo dicendum</em>, leaves its mark on his &quot;disciple&quot;
and gives him the ability to answer questions in Thomas&#39;s spirit that Thomas never asked and possibly at
that time could not have been asked at all.  </p>
<p>  This may well also be the reason why folks today are going back to his writings.  Ours is a time that 
is no longer content with methodical deliberations.  People have nothing to hold on to and are looking for
purchase.  They want a truth to cling to, a meaning for their lives; they want a &quot;philosophy for life.&quot; 
And this they find in Thomas.  </p>
<p>  Of course there is a difference between Thomas&#39;s philosophy and what passes for &quot;philosophy for life&quot;
today.  In his philosophy we will look in vain for flights of emotion; all we will find is truth, soberly
grasped in abstract concepts.  On the surface much of it looks like theoretical &quot;hairsplitting&quot; that we
cannot &quot;do&quot; anything with.  And even after serious study it is not easy to put our finger on practical
returns.  </p>
<p>  But a person who has lived for some time with the mind of St. Thomas – lucid, keen, calm, cautious – 
and dwelt in his world, will come to feel more and more that he is making right choices with ease and
confidence on difficult theoretical issues or in practical situations where before he would have been
helpless.  And if later he thinks back – even surprising himself – on how he managed it, he will realize
that a bit of Thomas&#39;s &quot;hairsplitting&quot; laid the groundwork.  At the time that Thomas was working on 
this or that problem, he naturally had no idea what it could someday be &quot;good for,&quot; nor was he concerned
about it.  He was but following otu the law of truth; truth bears fruit of itself.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>St. Edith Stein. <em>Knowledge and Faith.</em> tr. Walter Redmond. ICS Publications. 2000. pp.26-28</p>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>1980_sophocles_151508</title>
      <link>https://log.j38.uk/1980_sophocles_151508.html</link>
      <guid>https://log.j38.uk/1980_sophocles_151508.html</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>Many are the wonders, none<br>is more wonderful than what is man.<br>This it is that crosses the sea<br>with the south winds storming and the waves swelling,<br>breaking around him in roaring surf.<br>He it is again who wears away<br>the Earth, oldest of gods, immortal, unwearied,<br>as the ploughs wind across her from year to year<br>when he works her with the breed that comes from horses.<br>The tribe of the lighthearted birds he snares<br>and takes prisoner the races of savage beasts<br>and the brood of the fish of the sea,<br>with the close-spun web of nets.<br>A cunning fellow is man. His contrivances<br>make him master of beasts of the field<br>and those that move in the mountains.<br>So he brings the horse with the shaggy neck<br>to bend underneath the yoke;<br>and also the untamed mountain bull·<br>and speech and winds wift thought<br>and the tempers that go with city living<br>he has taught himself, and how to avoid<br>the sharp frost, when lodging is cold<br>under the open sky<br>and pelting strokes of the rain.<br>He has a way against everything,<br>and he faces nothing that is to come<br>without contrivance.<br>Only against death<br>can he call on no means of escape;<br>but escape from hopeless diseases<br>he has found in the depths of his mind.<br>With some sort of cunning, inventive<br>beyond all expectation<br>he reaches sometimes evil<br>and sometimes good.<br>If he honors the laws of earth,<br>and the justice of the gods he has confirmed by oath,<br>high is his city; no city<br>has he with whom dwells his honor<br>prompted by recklessness.<br>He who is so, may he never<br>share my hearth!<br>may he never think my thoughts!  </p>
</blockquote>
<p>Sophocles, <em>Antigone</em> 332-75. (tr. Lattimore)</p>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>1980_sophocles_151447</title>
      <link>https://log.j38.uk/1980_sophocles_151447.html</link>
      <guid>https://log.j38.uk/1980_sophocles_151447.html</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>Everything becomes hateful when a man abandons his own nature and acts at variance with it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>ἅπαντα δυσχέρεια, τὴν αὑτοῦ φύσιν / ὅταν λιπών τις δρᾷ τὰ μὴ προσεικότα.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Sophocles, <em>Philoctetes</em> 902.</p>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>1980_sophocles</title>
      <link>https://log.j38.uk/1980_sophocles.html</link>
      <guid>https://log.j38.uk/1980_sophocles.html</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>It is impossible to know any man–I mean his soul, intelligence, and judgement–until he shows his skill in rule and law. </p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>ἀήχανον δὲ παντὸς ἀνδρὸς ἐκμαθεῖν / ψυχήν τε καὶ φρόνημα καὶ γνώμην, πρὶν ἂν / ἀρχαῖς τε καὶ νόμοισιν ἐντριβὴς φανῇ.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Sophocles, <em>Antigone</em> 175-7 (tr. Lattimore).</p>
]]></description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>